Tracking Women's Health in the News

Home
Methodology
Visualization
Articles

Data Collection-General Methodology

Reviewed the health section (exact one reviewed specified under each below) of each news site
Took note of anything that pertains to women's health within the United States (US)
Looked for a "key" word in the title, including "women," "pregnancy," "abortion," "abortion-pill," "ivf," etc.
An id, place, key[word], lat, long, date, author, and source were recorded for each item
For place:

If it referenced a specific location, I used that.
If it spoke about a general health topic, but referenced the location of one main study, I used that.
If the article did not specify a specific place, I used "DC" as the location, as it is the US capital.
If the "place" is a state, the coordinates were inputted as the state's capital city.
If the location (ie, the NIH) has multiple locations, the coordinates of the headquarters were used.

1. New York Times Collection

Reviewed the title of all articles under the "health" section, back to November 1, 2023 (~6 months)

2. Washington Post Collection

Issue: paywell. I have a subscription to the NYT, but not the other news sites used. To get around this, I restricted my sources to the ones that I have access to through the University of Pittsburgh.
Searched through "health and well being" section on the Washington Post's site, and used those titles to search through the access site through the University of Pittsburgh.

3. Chicago Tribune Collection

Same issue with the paywell. However, these articles are available to University of Pittsburgh Students via PittCat as well.
Searched through "News > Health" Articles

Mapping and Visualization Methodology

I mapped the data using ArcGIS Online software, importing the data from .csv files.

The CSV files contained the following:

id: identification number.
place: location of where the research is happening or where the reporting is referencing.
lat: latitude.
long: longitude.
key: key word(s) from the title.
author: author of the article.
title: title of the article.
url: url of the article.

The maps displayed on the website are downloads of the maps created using ArcGIS online.
Next, I transformed all of the CSV files into XML files, using Regex to markup items so that each item from the CSV file was its own element.

Example to mark up <keys>:

find: ([key]),
replace:<key type="\1">\1</key>,

Using XSLT, I created a transformation to make a Chicago Style source list/bibliography for each XML page (ie, for each data base).

Issues With Collection/Methodology

The collection of data (ie, articles) was done by hand, so it is subject to human error.
Additionally, place was collected by hand, so it may also be subject to human error.
However, the general goal of this project is to get a sense of number of locations/reports done on women's health, and to allow users to find those studies easily.
Although the maps display the number of articles, I did not look to compare the number of articles published, so I did not control for number of total number of articles published in general by that news outlets. Neither did I compare to number of articles published specifically regarding men's health.

Tracking Women's Health in the News

Home
About
Maps
Articles
Conclusions

Wright, Jesse. Women’s health summit in South Holland seeks to address resources. Chicago Tribune, 4-21-2024. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2024/04/21/womens-health-summit-south-suburban-college/
Schencker, Lisa. Another 26 women sue Endeavor Health and gynecologist Fabio Ortega, convicted of sexual abuse. Chicago Tribune, 4-17-2024. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2024/04/17/fabio-ortega-endeavor-lawsuits/
Savage, Claire. New rules for Pregnant Workers Fairness Act include divisive accommodations for abortion. Chicago Tribune, 4-15-2024. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2024/04/15/new-rules-for-pregnant-workers-fairness-act-include-divisive-accommodations-for-abortion/
Knowles, Francine. Column: South suburban doctors propose solutions to combat high Black maternal death rates. Chicago Tribune, 4-15-2024. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2024/04/15/column-south-suburban-doctors-propose-solutions-to-combat-high-black-maternal-death-rates/
Associated Press, . Which states could have abortion on the ballot in 2024?. Chicago Tribune, 4-10-2024. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2024/04/10/abortion-ballot-questions/
Billeaud, Jacques. Arizona can enforce an 1864 law criminalizing nearly all abortions, court says. Chicago Tribune, 4-9-2024. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2024/04/09/an-arizona-court-ruling-makes-nearly-all-abortions-illegal-in-a-presidential-battleground-state/
Rockett, Darcel. Menstrual cycles can affect day-to-day suicide risk, UIC study finds. Chicago Tribune, 4-5-2024. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2024/04/05/menstrual-cycles-can-affect-day-to-day-suicide-risk-uic-study-finds/
Schencker, Lisa. More patients sue former Endeavor Health gynecologist Fabio Ortega, alleging sexual assault. Chicago Tribune, 4-1-2024. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2024/04/01/patients-sue-endeavor-health-fabio-ortega/
Hoerner, Emily. New lawsuit alleges abuse by former Endeavor Health gynecologist Fabio Ortega. Chicago Tribune, 3-26-2024. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2024/03/26/lawsuit-alleges-abuse-fabio-ortega/
Leventis Lourgos, Angie. Illinois poised to become a haven for out-of-state IVF patients amid conservative backlash. Chicago Tribune, 3-25-2024. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2024/03/24/illinois-poised-to-become-a-haven-for-out-of-state-ivf-patients-amid-conservative-backlash/
Rockett, Darcel. Breast cancer test may make bad chemotherapy recommendations for Black patients, UIC study shows. Chicago Tribune, 4-6-2024. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2024/03/22/breast-cancer-test-black-women-chemotherapy-uic/
Leventis Lourgos, Angie. Illinois abortion providers praise Walgreens, CVS plans to carry mifepristone. Chicago Tribune, 3-9-2024. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2024/03/09/illinois-abortion-providers-praise-walgreens-cvs-plans-to-carry-mifepristone/
Associated Press, . Alabama lawmakers advance legislation to protect IVF providers, with final approval still ahead. Chicago Tribune, 3-5-2024. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2024/03/05/alabama-lawmakers-advance-legislation-to-protect-ivf-providers-with-final-approval-still-ahead/
Associated Press, . First over-the-counter birth control pill in US begins shipping to stores. Chicago Tribune, 3-4-2024. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2024/03/04/first-over-the-counter-birth-control-pill-in-us-begins-shipping-to-stores/
New York Times News Service Syndicate, . For women undergoing IVF in Alabama, what now?. Chicago Tribune, 2-23-2024. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2024/02/23/alabama-ivf-whats-next/
Associated Press, . Alabama hospital puts pause on IVF in wake of ruling saying frozen embryos are children. Chicago Tribune, 2-21-2024. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2024/02/21/alabama-hospital-puts-pause-on-ivf-in-wake-of-ruling-saying-frozen-embryos-are-children/
Tribune News Service, . Mayo Clinic Minute: Health disparities in gynecologic cancers. Chicago Tribune, 2-20-2024. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2024/02/20/mayo-clinic-minute-health-disparities-in-gynecologic-cancers/
Rockett, Darcel. SheRo Program from social services agency UCAN Chicago helps heal women most at risk for violence. Chicago Tribune, 2-16-2024. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2024/02/16/ucan-shero-program-for-women/
Associated Press, . Lupus and other autoimmune diseases strike far more women than men. Now there’s a clue why. Chicago Tribune, 2-1-2024. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2024/02/01/lupus-and-other-autoimmune-diseases-strike-far-more-women-than-men-now-theres-a-clue-why/
Tribune Content Agency, . Mayo Clinic Q&A: What to know about cervical cancer. Chicago Tribune, 1-26-2024. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2024/01/26/mayo-clinic-qa-what-to-know-about-cervical-cancer/
Lourgos, Angie Leventis. Illinois abortions surged the year Roe fell, with nearly 17,000 patients traveling from other states — a 49% spike. Chicago Tribune, 2-7-2024. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2024/01/10/illinois-abortions-surged-the-year-roe-fell-with-nearly-17000-patients-traveling-from-other-states-a-49-spike/
Guffey, Alysa. AI model developed by Northwestern researchers could suggest better treatment plans for breast cancer patients. Chicago Tribune, 12-23-2023. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2023/12/23/ai-model-developed-by-northwestern-researchers-could-suggest-better-treatment-plans-for-breast-cancer-patients/
Rockett, Darcel. New campaign aims to turn the tide on maternal mortality in Chicago’s Black community. Chicago Tribune, 12-22-2023. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2023/12/22/new-campaign-aims-to-turn-the-tide-on-maternal-mortality-in-chicagos-black-community/
Associated Press, . Wisconsin district attorney appeals ruling that cleared way for abortions to resume in state. Chicago Tribune, 12-20-2023. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2023/12/20/wisconsin-district-attorney-appeals-ruling-that-cleared-way-for-abortions-to-resume-in-state/
Neumann, Janice. Teachers at same Romeoville school become ‘breasties’ over shared cancer fight. Chicago Tribune, 11-6-2023. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2023/11/06/teachers-at-same-romeoville-school-become-breasties-over-shared-cancer-fight/

Tracking Women's Health in the News

Home
About
Maps
Articles
Conclusions

Bazelon, Emily. "Why ‘Fetal Personhood’ Is Roiling the Right." New York Times, 3-3-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/03/03/magazine/fetal-personhood-alabama-ivf.html.
Belluck, Pam. "4 Takeaways From the Abortion Pill Arguments." New York Times, 3-26-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/03/26/us/politics/abortion-pill-supreme-court-takeaways.html.
Belluck, Pam. "Abortion Shield Laws: A New War Between the States." New York Times, 2-22-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/02/22/health/abortion-shield-laws-telemedicine.html.
Belluck, Pam. ""Abortions by Telemedicine and Mailed Pills Are Safe and Effective, Study Finds"." New York Times, 2-15-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/02/15/health/abortion-pills-mail-safety.html.
Belluck, Pam. "CVS and Walgreens Will Begin Selling Abortion Pills This Month." New York Times, 3-1-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/03/01/health/abortion-pills-cvs-walgreens.html.
Belluck, Pam. "First U.S. Over-the-Counter Birth Control Pill Will Be Available Soon." New York Times, 3-4-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/03/04/health/opill-birth-control-nonprescription.html.
Belluck, Pam. "Journal Retracts Studies Cited in Federal Court Ruling Against Abortion Pill." New York Times, 2-9-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/02/09/health/abortion-pills-study-retraction.html.
Belluck, Pam. "More Women Who Are Not Pregnant Are Ordering Abortion Pills Just in Case." New York Times, 1-2-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/01/02/health/abortion-pills-advanced-provision.html.
Belluck, Pam. "The History Behind Arizona’s 160-Year-Old Abortion Ban." New York Times, 4-10-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/04/10/health/arizona-abortion-ban-history.html.
Belluck, Pam. ""Use of Abortion Pills Has Risen Significantly Post Roe, Research Shows"." New York Times, 3-25-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/03/25/health/abortion-pills.html.
Belluck, Pam. "What to Know About the Federal Law at the Heart of the Latest Supreme Court Abortion Case." New York Times, 1-18-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/01/18/health/emtala-abortion-supreme-court.html.
Friedman, Danielle. "A Brief History of Sexism in Medicine." New York Times, 2-26-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/02/26/well/live/women-health-care-elizabeth-comen.html.
Ghorayshi, Azeen and Sarah Kliff. ""Accidents, Lax Rules and Abortion Laws Now Imperil Fertility Industry"." New York Times, 2-22-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/02/22/health/fertility-clinics-embryos-alabama.html.
Goldberg, Emma. ""Hospitals Must Get Written Patient Consent for Pelvic Exams, H.H.S. Says"." New York Times, 4-1-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/04/01/health/pelvic-exam-consent-unconcious.html.
Hoffman, Jan. "Alabama Says Embryos in a Lab Are Children. What Are the Implications?." New York Times, 2-21-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/02/21/health/ivf-frozen-embryos.html.
Hoffman, Jan. "Alabama’s I.V.F. Protection Law Will Reopen Clinics but Curb Patient Rights." New York Times, 3-6-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/03/06/health/ivf-law-alabama.html.
Kliff, Sarah. "Major Embryo Shipping Company Halts Business in Alabama." New York Times, 2-23-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/02/23/health/embryo-shipping-alabama-ivf.html.
Mandavilli, Apoorva. "Some Pregnant Women and Infants Received the Wrong R.S.V. Shots." New York Times, 2-14-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/02/14/health/rsv-shots-pregnant-women-infants.html.
Miller, Claire Cain and Margot Sanger-Katz. ""One in Six Abortions Is Done With Pills Prescribed Online, Data Shows"." New York Times, 2-28-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/02/28/upshot/abortion-pills-prescribed-online.html.
Rabin, Roni Caryn. "How a Sudden Halt to In Vitro Fertilization Shook Alabama Couples." New York Times, 3-7-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/03/07/health/ivf-alabama-families.html.
Rabin, Roni Caryn. "How Bias Endangers Pregnant Black Women." New York Times, 12-29-2023. https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2023/12/29/health/bias-pregnant-black-women.html.
Rabin, Roni Caryn. "How Unconscious Bias in Health Care Puts Pregnant Black Women at Higher Risk." New York Times, 12-12-2023. https://www.nytimes.com/2023/12/12/health/pregnant-black-women-bias.html.
Rabin, Roni Caryn and Azeen Ghorayshi. ""Alabama Rules Frozen Embryos Are Children, Raising Questions About Fertility Care"." New York Times, 2-20-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/02/20/health/ivf-alabama-abortion.html.
Sanger-Katz, Margot and Claire Cain Miller. "How Many Abortions Did the Post-Roe Bans Prevent?." New York Times, 11-22-2023. https://www.nytimes.com/2023/11/22/upshot/abortion-births-bans-states.html.
Sarah Kliff, Azeen Ghorayshi. ""Botched I.V.F. Liquid Destroyed Embryos, Lawsuits Claim"." New York Times, 2-15-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/02/15/health/cooper-surgical-ivf-embryos-lawsuits.html.
Smith, Rory. ""Silent No More, Women’s Pros Make Mental Health a Priority"." New York Times, 1-12-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/01/12/world/europe/mental-health-womens-soccer.html.
Span, Paula. "The Heart Surgery That Isn’t as Safe for Older Women." New York Times, 1-20-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/01/20/health/heart-bypass-women.html.
VanSickle, Abbie. "Supreme Court Will Hear Challenge to Abortion Pill Access." New York Times, 12-13-2023. https://www.nytimes.com/2023/12/13/us/supreme-court-abortion-pill.html.
VanSickle, Abbie and Pam Belluck. "Abortion Pill Dispute Centers on Central Question: Who Can Sue?." New York Times, 3-26-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/03/26/us/politics/abortion-pill-lawsuits-doctors.html.
Zimmer, Carl. "Why Do Women Have More Autoimmune Diseases? Study Points to X Chromosome." New York Times, 2-1-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/02/01/health/women-autoimmune-disease-x-chromosome.html.

Tracking Women's Health in the News

Home
Methodology
Visualization
Articles

Chicago Tribune Articles

Associated Press. "Alabama hospital puts pause on IVF in wake of ruling saying frozen embryos are children." Chicago Tribune, 2-21-2024. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2024/02/21/alabama-hospital-puts-pause-on-ivf-in-wake-of-ruling-saying-frozen-embryos-are-children/.
Associated Press. "Alabama lawmakers advance legislation to protect IVF providers, with final approval still ahead." Chicago Tribune, 3-5-2024. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2024/03/05/alabama-lawmakers-advance-legislation-to-protect-ivf-providers-with-final-approval-still-ahead/.
Associated Press. "First over-the-counter birth control pill in US begins shipping to stores." Chicago Tribune, 3-4-2024. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2024/03/04/first-over-the-counter-birth-control-pill-in-us-begins-shipping-to-stores/.
Associated Press. "Lupus and other autoimmune diseases strike far more women than men. Now there’s a clue why." Chicago Tribune, 2-1-2024. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2024/02/01/lupus-and-other-autoimmune-diseases-strike-far-more-women-than-men-now-theres-a-clue-why/.
Associated Press. "Wisconsin district attorney appeals ruling that cleared way for abortions to resume in state." Chicago Tribune, 12-20-2023. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2023/12/20/wisconsin-district-attorney-appeals-ruling-that-cleared-way-for-abortions-to-resume-in-state/.
Associated Press. "Which states could have abortion on the ballot in 2024?" Chicago Tribune, 4-10-2024. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2024/04/10/abortion-ballot-questions/.
Billeaud, Jacques. "Arizona can enforce an 1864 law criminalizing nearly all abortions, court says." Chicago Tribune, 4-9-2024. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2024/04/09/an-arizona-court-ruling-makes-nearly-all-abortions-illegal-in-a-presidential-battleground-state/.
Guffey, Alysa. "AI model developed by Northwestern researchers could suggest better treatment plans for breast cancer patients." Chicago Tribune, 12-23-2023. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2023/12/23/ai-model-developed-by-northwestern-researchers-could-suggest-better-treatment-plans-for-breast-cancer-patients/.
Hoerner, Emily. "New lawsuit alleges abuse by former Endeavor Health gynecologist Fabio Ortega." Chicago Tribune, 3-26-2024. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2024/03/26/lawsuit-alleges-abuse-fabio-ortega/.
Knowles, Francine. "Column: South suburban doctors propose solutions to combat high Black maternal death rates." Chicago Tribune, 4-15-2024. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2024/04/15/column-south-suburban-doctors-propose-solutions-to-combat-high-black-maternal-death-rates/.
Lourgos, Angie Leventis. "Illinois abortion providers praise Walgreens, CVS plans to carry mifepristone." Chicago Tribune, 3-9-2024. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2024/03/09/illinois-abortion-providers-praise-walgreens-cvs-plans-to-carry-mifepristone/.
Lourgos, Angie Leventis. "Illinois abortions surged the year Roe fell, with nearly 17,000 patients traveling from other states — a 49% spike." Chicago Tribune, 2-7-2024. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2024/01/10/illinois-abortions-surged-the-year-roe-fell-with-nearly-17000-patients-traveling-from-other-states-a-49-spike/.
Lourgos, Angie Leventis. "Illinois poised to become a haven for out-of-state IVF patients amid conservative backlash." Chicago Tribune, 3-25-2024. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2024/03/24/illinois-poised-to-become-a-haven-for-out-of-state-ivf-patients-amid-conservative-backlash/.
Neumann, Janice. "Teachers at same Romeoville school become ‘breasties’ over shared cancer fight." Chicago Tribune, 11-6-2023. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2023/11/06/teachers-at-same-romeoville-school-become-breasties-over-shared-cancer-fight/.
New York Times News Service Syndicate. "For women undergoing IVF in Alabama, what now?" Chicago Tribune, 2-23-2024. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2024/02/23/alabama-ivf-whats-next/.
Rockett, Darcel. "Breast cancer test may make bad chemotherapy recommendations for Black patients, UIC study shows." Chicago Tribune, 4-6-2024. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2024/03/22/breast-cancer-test-black-women-chemotherapy-uic/.
Rockett, Darcel. "Menstrual cycles can affect day-to-day suicide risk, UIC study finds." Chicago Tribune, 4-5-2024. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2024/04/05/menstrual-cycles-can-affect-day-to-day-suicide-risk-uic-study-finds/.
Rockett, Darcel. "New campaign aims to turn the tide on maternal mortality in Chicago’s Black community." Chicago Tribune, 12-22-2023. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2023/12/22/new-campaign-aims-to-turn-the-tide-on-maternal-mortality-in-chicagos-black-community/.
Rockett, Darcel. "SheRo Program from social services agency UCAN Chicago helps heal women most at risk for violence." Chicago Tribune, 2-16-2024. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2024/02/16/ucan-shero-program-for-women/.
Savage, Claire. "New rules for Pregnant Workers Fairness Act include divisive accommodations for abortion." Chicago Tribune, 4-15-2024. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2024/04/15/new-rules-for-pregnant-workers-fairness-act-include-divisive-accommodations-for-abortion/.
Schencker, Lisa. "Another 26 women sue Endeavor Health and gynecologist Fabio Ortega, convicted of sexual abuse." Chicago Tribune, 4-17-2024. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2024/04/17/fabio-ortega-endeavor-lawsuits/.
Schencker, Lisa. "More patients sue former Endeavor Health gynecologist Fabio Ortega, alleging sexual assault." Chicago Tribune, 4-1-2024. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2024/04/01/patients-sue-endeavor-health-fabio-ortega/.
Tribune Content Agency. "Mayo Clinic Q&A: What to know about cervical cancer." Chicago Tribune, 1-26-2024. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2024/01/26/mayo-clinic-qa-what-to-know-about-cervical-cancer/.
Tribune News Service. "Mayo Clinic Minute: Health disparities in gynecologic cancers." Chicago Tribune, 2-20-2024. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2024/02/20/mayo-clinic-minute-health-disparities-in-gynecologic-cancers/.
Wright, Jesse. "Women’s health summit in South Holland seeks to address resources." Chicago Tribune, 4-21-2024. https://www.chicagotribune.com/2024/04/21/womens-health-summit-south-suburban-college/.

New York Times Articles

Bazelon, Emily. "Why ‘Fetal Personhood’ Is Roiling the Right." New York Times, 3-3-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/03/03/magazine/fetal-personhood-alabama-ivf.html.
Belluck, Pam. "4 Takeaways From the Abortion Pill Arguments." New York Times, 3-26-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/03/26/us/politics/abortion-pill-supreme-court-takeaways.html.
Belluck, Pam. "Abortion Shield Laws: A New War Between the States." New York Times, 2-22-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/02/22/health/abortion-shield-laws-telemedicine.html.
Belluck, Pam. "Abortions by Telemedicine and Mailed Pills Are Safe and Effective, Study Finds." New York Times, 2-15-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/02/15/health/abortion-pills-mail-safety.html.
Belluck, Pam. "CVS and Walgreens Will Begin Selling Abortion Pills This Month." New York Times, 3-1-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/03/01/health/abortion-pills-cvs-walgreens.html.
Belluck, Pam. "First U.S. Over-the-Counter Birth Control Pill Will Be Available Soon." New York Times, 3-4-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/03/04/health/opill-birth-control-nonprescription.html.
Belluck, Pam. "Journal Retracts Studies Cited in Federal Court Ruling Against Abortion Pill." New York Times, 2-9-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/02/09/health/abortion-pills-study-retraction.html.
Belluck, Pam. "More Women Who Are Not Pregnant Are Ordering Abortion Pills Just in Case." New York Times, 1-2-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/01/02/health/abortion-pills-advanced-provision.html.
Belluck, Pam. "The History Behind Arizona’s 160-Year-Old Abortion Ban." New York Times, 4-10-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/04/10/health/arizona-abortion-ban-history.html.
Belluck, Pam. "Use of Abortion Pills Has Risen Significantly Post Roe, Research Shows." New York Times, 3-25-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/03/25/health/abortion-pills.html.
Belluck, Pam. "What to Know About the Federal Law at the Heart of the Latest Supreme Court Abortion Case." New York Times, 1-18-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/01/18/health/emtala-abortion-supreme-court.html.
Friedman, Danielle. "A Brief History of Sexism in Medicine." New York Times, 2-26-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/02/26/well/live/women-health-care-elizabeth-comen.html.
Ghorayshi, Azeen and Sarah Kliff. "Accidents, Lax Rules and Abortion Laws Now Imperil Fertility Industry." New York Times, 2-22-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/02/22/health/fertility-clinics-embryos-alabama.html.
Goldberg, Emma. "Hospitals Must Get Written Patient Consent for Pelvic Exams, H.H.S. Says." New York Times, 4-1-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/04/01/health/pelvic-exam-consent-unconcious.html.
Hoffman, Jan. "Alabama Says Embryos in a Lab Are Children. What Are the Implications?." New York Times, 2-21-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/02/21/health/ivf-frozen-embryos.html.
Hoffman, Jan. "Alabama’s I.V.F. Protection Law Will Reopen Clinics but Curb Patient Rights." New York Times, 3-6-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/03/06/health/ivf-law-alabama.html.
Kliff, Sarah. "Major Embryo Shipping Company Halts Business in Alabama." New York Times, 2-23-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/02/23/health/embryo-shipping-alabama-ivf.html.
Mandavilli, Apoorva. "Some Pregnant Women and Infants Received the Wrong R.S.V. Shots." New York Times, 2-14-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/02/14/health/rsv-shots-pregnant-women-infants.html.
Miller, Claire Cain and Margot Sanger-Katz. ""One in Six Abortions Is Done With Pills Prescribed Online, Data Shows"." New York Times, 2-28-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/02/28/upshot/abortion-pills-prescribed-online.html.
Rabin, Roni Caryn. "How a Sudden Halt to In Vitro Fertilization Shook Alabama Couples." New York Times, 3-7-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/03/07/health/ivf-alabama-families.html.
Rabin, Roni Caryn. "How Bias Endangers Pregnant Black Women." New York Times, 12-29-2023. https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2023/12/29/health/bias-pregnant-black-women.html.
Rabin, Roni Caryn. "How Unconscious Bias in Health Care Puts Pregnant Black Women at Higher Risk." New York Times, 12-12-2023. https://www.nytimes.com/2023/12/12/health/pregnant-black-women-bias.html.
Rabin, Roni Caryn and Azeen Ghorayshi. "Alabama Rules Frozen Embryos Are Children, Raising Questions About Fertility Care." New York Times, 2-20-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/02/20/health/ivf-alabama-abortion.html.
Sanger-Katz, Margot and Claire Cain Miller. "How Many Abortions Did the Post-Roe Bans Prevent?." New York Times, 11-22-2023. https://www.nytimes.com/2023/11/22/upshot/abortion-births-bans-states.html.
Sarah Kliff, Azeen Ghorayshi. "Botched I.V.F. Liquid Destroyed Embryos, Lawsuits Claim." New York Times, 2-15-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/02/15/health/cooper-surgical-ivf-embryos-lawsuits.html.
Smith, Rory. "Silent No More, Women’s Pros Make Mental Health a Priority." New York Times, 1-12-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/01/12/world/europe/mental-health-womens-soccer.html.
Span, Paula. "The Heart Surgery That Isn’t as Safe for Older Women." New York Times, 1-20-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/01/20/health/heart-bypass-women.html.
VanSickle, Abbie. "Supreme Court Will Hear Challenge to Abortion Pill Access." New York Times, 12-13-2023. https://www.nytimes.com/2023/12/13/us/supreme-court-abortion-pill.html.
VanSickle, Abbie and Pam Belluck. "Abortion Pill Dispute Centers on Central Question: Who Can Sue?" New York Times, 3-26-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/03/26/us/politics/abortion-pill-lawsuits-doctors.html.
Zimmer, Carl. "Why Do Women Have More Autoimmune Diseases? Study Points to X Chromosome." New York Times, 2-1-2024. https://www.nytimes.com/2024/02/01/health/women-autoimmune-disease-x-chromosome.html.

Washington Post Articles

Ables, Kelsey. "What is Trisomy 18, the fetal condition central to the Texas abortion case?" Washington Post, 12-13-2023. https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/2023/12/13/texas-abortion-trisomy-18-diagnosis/.
Blakemore, Erin. "Study undercuts premise for excluding women from medical research." Washington Post, 11-18-2023. https://www.washingtonpost.com/wellness/2023/11/18/women-body-temperature-medical-research/.
Cimons, Marlene. "Do women who live together get their periods together, or is it a myth?" Washington Post, 4-22-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/wellness/2024/04/22/women-menstruation-periods-synchrony/.
Cornejo, Drea, et. al. "Three couples and their IVF hopes, jolted by Alabama’s court ruling." Washington Post, 3-8-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/interactive/2024/ivf-couples-alabama-ruling/.
Dewey, Caitlin. "Abortion debate is affecting access to drug used after miscarriages." Washington Post, 11-5-2023. https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/2023/11/05/mifepristone-miscarriage-abortion-fallout/.
Diamond, Dan. "Alito and Thomas kept bringing up Comstock. That scared abortion rights supporters." Washington Post, 3-26-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/2024/03/26/comstock-act-supreme-court-abortion-pill/.
Diamond, Dan and Caroline Kitchener. "Texas doctors do not need to perform emergency abortions, court rules." Washington Post, 1-3-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/2024/01/02/texas-abortion-emergency-5th-circuit/.
Gilber, Daniel. "Alabama IVF ruling draws attention to technology’s unregulated frontiers." Washington Post, 3-7-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/business/2024/03/07/alabama-ivf-sex-selection-ethics/.
Javaid, Maham and Dan Rosenzweig-Ziff. "What to know about the Alabama embryo ruling and its IVF implications." Washington Post, 2-21-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/nation/2024/02/20/ivf-treatment-alabama-embryo-ruling/.
Javaid, Maham and Kim Bellware. "Some Alabama clinics pause IVF services amid scramble for next steps." Washington Post, 2-21-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/nation/2024/02/21/alabama-ivf-clinics-doctors-embryo-ruling/.
Johnson, Akilah. "For some Black women, the fear of death shadows the joy of birth." Washington Post, 12-14-2023. https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/interactive/2023/black-women-pregnancy-mortality-fear/.
Johnson, Mark and Sabrina Malhi. "Scientists found a major clue why 4 of 5 autoimmune patients are women." Washington Post, 2-1-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/science/2024/02/01/why-women-have-more-autoimmune-diseases/.
Kitchener, Caroline. "‘No help here’: Florida abortion ruling leaves women with few options." Washington Post, 4-2-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/nation/2024/04/02/florida-supreme-court-abortion-access/.
Kitchener, Caroline. "Periods, ‘live tissue’: Female justices get specific about women’s health." Washington Post, 3-26-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2024/03/26/women-justices-abortion-pill/.
Malhi, Sabrina. "Amid syphilis surge, doctors call for more testing during pregnancy." Washington Post, 4-18-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/2024/04/18/screening-syphilis-baby-pregnant/.
Malhi, Sabrina. "Cannabis use linked to higher risk of poor pregnancy outcomes, study finds." Washington Post, 12-12-2023. https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/2023/12/12/cannabis-use-pregnancy-postpartum-study/.
Malhi, Sabrina. "Overdose deaths have soared among pregnant people, study reveals." Washington Post, 11-22-2023. https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/2023/11/22/overdose-pregnancy-opioids/.
Malhi, Sabrina. "What to know about PCOS and the newfound link to cognitive decline." Washington Post, 2-6-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/2024/02/06/pcos-cognitive-health-explained/.
Malhi, Sabrina and Dan Diamond. "What Biden’s latest actions on reproductive health mean." Washington Post, 1-25-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/2024/01/25/contraception-emergency-abortion-access-biden/.
Malhi, Sabrina and Dan Keating. "Study says U.S. maternal death rate crisis is really a case of bad data." Washington Post, 3-13-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/2024/03/13/maternal-mortality-study/.
Malhi, Sabrina and Kendra Nicholas. "Opill, first U.S. over-the-counter birth-control pill, to hit stores: What to know." Washington Post, 3-7-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/2024/03/05/opill-birth-control-pill-over-the-counter/.
Malhi, Sabrina and Lauren Weber. "Debunking common birth-control misconceptions." Washington Post, 3-21-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/2024/03/21/birth-control-facts/.
Malhi, Sabrina and McKenzie Beard. "How abortion pill mifepristone is used, and where you can legally access it." Washington Post, 3-25-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/2024/03/25/mifepristone-abortion-pill-access/.
Marimow, Ann E. "Abortion, guns and the state of a divided Supreme Court." Washington Post, 3-25-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/podcasts/post-reports/abortion-guns-and-the-state-of-a-divided-supreme-court/.
Marimow, Ann E. "Supreme Court to decide if U.S. law requires some emergency room abortions." Washington Post, 1-6-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2024/01/05/abortion-idaho-supreme-court-hospitals-emtala/.
Marimow, Ann E. and Caroline Kitchener. "Supreme Court skeptical of efforts to restrict access to abortion pill." Washington Post, 3-26-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2024/03/26/supreme-court-abortion-pill-mifepristone/.
Marimow, Ann E. and Caroline Kitchener. "What’s at stake in the Supreme Court abortion pill case." Washington Post, 3-24-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2024/03/24/supreme-court-abortion-pill-case/.
Marinmow, Ann E. "Supreme Court will decide access to key abortion drug mifepristone." Washington Post, 12-13-2023. https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2023/12/13/abortion-drug-supreme-court-mifepristone-fda/.
Rosenzweig-Ziff, Dan. "U.S. abortions reach recent high, with record number done via medication." Washington Post, 3-19-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2024/03/19/abortion-medication-mifepristone-63-percent/.
Searing, Linda. "Lung cancer is more common among women than men ages 35 to 54." Washington Post, 10-31-2023. https://www.washingtonpost.com/wellness/2023/10/31/lung-cancer-rate-women-men/.
Weber, Lauren and Sabrina Malhi. "Women are getting off birth control amid misinformation explosion." Washington Post, 3-21-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/2024/03/21/stopping-birth-control-misinformation/.
Wootson, Cleve R. and Dan Diamond. "Harris, Biden deliver fiery message on abortion rights." Washington Post, 1-22-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/2024/01/22/biden-abortion-contraception/.

Tracking Women's Health in the News

Home
About
Maps
Articles
Conclusions

Ables, Kelsey. ""What is Trisomy 18, the fetal condition central to the Texas abortion case?"." Washington Post, 12-13-2023. https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/2023/12/13/texas-abortion-trisomy-18-diagnosis/.
Blakemore, Erin. "Study undercuts premise for excluding women from medical research." Washington Post, 11-18-2023. https://www.washingtonpost.com/wellness/2023/11/18/women-body-temperature-medical-research/.
Cimons, Marlene. ""Do women who live together get their periods together, or is it a myth?"." Washington Post, 4-22-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/wellness/2024/04/22/women-menstruation-periods-synchrony/.
Cornejo, Drea, et. al. . ""Three couples and their IVF hopes, jolted by Alabama’s court ruling"." Washington Post, 3-8-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/interactive/2024/ivf-couples-alabama-ruling/.
Dewey, Caitlin. "Abortion debate is affecting access to drug used after miscarriages." Washington Post, 11-5-2023. https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/2023/11/05/mifepristone-miscarriage-abortion-fallout/.
Diamond, Dan. "Alito and Thomas kept bringing up Comstock. That scared abortion rights supporters.." Washington Post, 3-26-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/2024/03/26/comstock-act-supreme-court-abortion-pill/.
Diamond, Dan and Caroline Kitchener. ""Texas doctors do not need to perform emergency abortions, court rules"." Washington Post, 1-3-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/2024/01/02/texas-abortion-emergency-5th-circuit/.
Gilber, Daniel . "Alabama IVF ruling draws attention to technology’s unregulated frontiers." Washington Post, 3-7-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/business/2024/03/07/alabama-ivf-sex-selection-ethics/.
Javaid, Maham and Dan Rosenzweig-Ziff. "What to know about the Alabama embryo ruling and its IVF implications." Washington Post, 2-21-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/nation/2024/02/20/ivf-treatment-alabama-embryo-ruling/.
Javaid, Maham and Kim Bellware. "Some Alabama clinics pause IVF services amid scramble for next steps." Washington Post, 2-21-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/nation/2024/02/21/alabama-ivf-clinics-doctors-embryo-ruling/.
Johnson, Akilah. ""For some Black women, the fear of death shadows the joy of birth"." Washington Post, 12-14-2023. https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/interactive/2023/black-women-pregnancy-mortality-fear/.
Johnson, Mark and Sabrina Malhi. "Scientists found a major clue why 4 of 5 autoimmune patients are women." Washington Post, 2-1-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/science/2024/02/01/why-women-have-more-autoimmune-diseases/.
Kitchener, Caroline. "‘No help here’: Florida abortion ruling leaves women with few options." Washington Post, 4-2-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/nation/2024/04/02/florida-supreme-court-abortion-access/.
Kitchener, Caroline. ""Periods, ‘live tissue’: Female justices get specific about women’s health"." Washington Post, 3-26-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2024/03/26/women-justices-abortion-pill/.
Malhi, Sabrina. ""Amid syphilis surge, doctors call for more testing during pregnancy"." Washington Post, 4-18-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/2024/04/18/screening-syphilis-baby-pregnant/.
Malhi, Sabrina. ""Cannabis use linked to higher risk of poor pregnancy outcomes, study finds"." Washington Post, 12-12-2023. https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/2023/12/12/cannabis-use-pregnancy-postpartum-study/.
Malhi, Sabrina. ""Overdose deaths have soared among pregnant people, study reveals"." Washington Post, 11-22-2023. https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/2023/11/22/overdose-pregnancy-opioids/.
Malhi, Sabrina. "What to know about PCOS and the newfound link to cognitive decline." Washington Post, 2-6-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/2024/02/06/pcos-cognitive-health-explained/.
Malhi, Sabrina and Dan Diamond. "What Biden’s latest actions on reproductive health mean." Washington Post, 1-25-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/2024/01/25/contraception-emergency-abortion-access-biden/.
Malhi, Sabrina and Dan Keating. "Study says U.S. maternal death rate crisis is really a case of bad data." Washington Post, 3-13-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/2024/03/13/maternal-mortality-study/.
Malhi, Sabrina and Kendra Nicholas. ""Opill, first U.S. over-the-counter birth-control pill, to hit stores: What to know"." Washington Post, 3-7-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/2024/03/05/opill-birth-control-pill-over-the-counter/.
Malhi, Sabrina and Lauren Weber. "Debunking common birth-control misconceptions." Washington Post, 3-21-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/2024/03/21/birth-control-facts/.
Malhi, Sabrina and McKenzie Beard. ""How abortion pill mifepristone is used, and where you can legally access it"." Washington Post, 3-25-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/2024/03/25/mifepristone-abortion-pill-access/.
Marimow, Ann E. ""Abortion, guns and the state of a divided Supreme Court"." Washington Post, 3-25-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/podcasts/post-reports/abortion-guns-and-the-state-of-a-divided-supreme-court/.
Marimow, Ann E. "Supreme Court to decide if U.S. law requires some emergency room abortions." Washington Post, 1-6-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2024/01/05/abortion-idaho-supreme-court-hospitals-emtala/.
Marimow, Ann E. and Caroline Kitchener. "Supreme Court skeptical of efforts to restrict access to abortion pill." Washington Post, 3-26-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2024/03/26/supreme-court-abortion-pill-mifepristone/.
Marimow, Ann E. and Caroline Kitchener. "What’s at stake in the Supreme Court abortion pill case." Washington Post, 3-24-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2024/03/24/supreme-court-abortion-pill-case/.
Marinmow, Ann E. "Supreme Court will decide access to key abortion drug mifepristone." Washington Post, 12-13-2023. https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2023/12/13/abortion-drug-supreme-court-mifepristone-fda/.
Rosenzweig-Ziff, Dan. ""U.S. abortions reach recent high, with record number done via medication"." Washington Post, 3-19-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2024/03/19/abortion-medication-mifepristone-63-percent/.
Searing, Linda. "Lung cancer is more common among women than men ages 35 to 54." Washington Post, 10-31-2023. https://www.washingtonpost.com/wellness/2023/10/31/lung-cancer-rate-women-men/.
Weber, Lauren and Sabrina Malhi. "Women are getting off birth control amid misinformation explosion." Washington Post, 3-21-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/2024/03/21/stopping-birth-control-misinformation/.
Wootson, Cleve R. and Dan Diamond. ""Harris, Biden deliver fiery message on abortion rights"." Washington Post, 1-22-2024. https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/2024/01/22/biden-abortion-contraception/.

Tracking Women's Health in the News

Home
Methodology
Visualization
Articles

Goal of This Project

Women's health has been a historically understudied and area of medicine. According to the Association of American Medical Colleges, women were not even included in clinical trials until the mid-1990s.[1] However, differences in biological sex can cause different reactions to those assigned female at birth (AFAB) than those assigned male at birth (AMAB).[2] This project seeks to promote research specifically regarding those AFAB by setting up a "database" which will track reporting by major news outlets. Rather than serving as a research database, this will serve more as a collection of research and reporting that relates to the health of those AFAB. It's ultimate goal is to demonstrate where in the United States research and reporting is happening, and to serve as a location that health sources relating to those AFAB can be found. Currently, this site tracks the reporting of three news outlets: the Chicago tribune, the New York Times, and the Washington Post. However, ideally, this site will expand to track more than just three news outlets, and would additionally track current research studies/clinical trials that relate to the health of those AFAB.

About the Creator

Madeline Franz is a junior at the University of Pittsburgh, majoring in Political Science and History, and minoring in Computer Science and French.
This project was developed as a final assignment for the GSWS 0400 course.
Note: This was developed independently of any organizations mentioned.
Description for why I chose to create this & how it reflects what I learned in this class:

This project was originally inspired by two things: 1) the work we did for this course in Pitt's archives, and 2) my HIST 1030: Computational Methods in the Humanities course. During my work in the archives, I was inspired to mark up and compare different texts/different data, using what I learned in HIST 1030, for my final project for GSWS 0400. However, the texts I worked with (the Medical Oaths) were not easily found digitally. So, I started to think of other ways that I could represent the disparities between those AMAB and those AFAB in the medical community. I wanted to create a website that not only acknowledged the lack of research, but also served as a resource to show where in the world research and reporting on those AFAB was happening. The first obstacle was finding this research. I tried multiple different avenues: for example, I tried to find reports on popular drugs in order to compare the sex of those studies. However, overtime, the idea developed to what it is now. Although this is just serving as a final project for my GSWS course, it feels incomplete. One major area that it is missing it the locations where current research is happening. In theory, as briefly discussed above, this would be a "real" database, and would be continually updated from the three news sources I used, and would expand to include other news outlets, as well as general research that is happening.
Going into my the course, I knew that pharmesetical and medical research mostly focused on those AMAB. However, this course pushed me to go into more depth regarding why that happened, and how those who didn't identify as male were oftentimes pushed out of the workplace, not credited for their work, etc. This project hopes to recognize the place that those AFAB have not only as the researchers, but the place they need as the subjects themselves in order to better support their health.

[1] Bridget Balch, "Why We Know So Little About Women's Health," AAMC, March 26. 2024, https://www.aamc.org/news/why-we-know-so-little-about-women-s-health#:~:text=Historical%20bias%2C%20policies%20designed%20to,best%20to%20treat%20them%20for.

[2] IBID.